Guide to the Daniel and Philip Berrigan collection, 1880-1995
Berrigan, Daniel and Philip collection, 1880-1995
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Daniel and Philip Berrigan Collection, 1880-1995
4602
Daniel Berrigan.
Philip Berrigan.
207 cubic ft.
Correspondence, legal documents, manuscripts of poetry and prose writings, notes for talks, periodical articles, newspaper clippings, photographs, broadsides, tape recordings, videocassettes, microfilms.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Personal papers and ephemeral publications by and about Daniel and Philip Berrigan.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
The brothers Daniel Berrigan (born 1921) and Philip Berrigan (born 1923) have both been prominent in resistance to racial segregation, to U.S. involvement in the Vietnam war, and to the production of nuclear weapons. Philip Berrigan, a former Josephite priest, and Daniel, a Jesuit priest, poet, playwright, and teacher, are both lecturers and civil disobedience activists.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Personal papers and ephemeral publications by and about Daniel and Philip Berrigan, including correspondence, legal documents, manuscripts of poetry and prose writings, notes for talks, periodical arcticles, newspaper clippings, photographs, broadsides, tape recordings, videocassettes, and microfilms. The greater part of the collection consists of papers dated after 1960 and contains much on the Catonsville Nine, the Harrisburg Seven, and the Plowshares Eight. Earlier material includes some Berrigan family history. The collection is supplemented by published books by and about the Berrigans. Also twelve letters of correspondence with Ross Labrie.
Also a broadside from the "America is Hard to Find" weekend, April 17-19, 1970; and a videocassette "America is Hard to Find," - Spring 1970. Video: "The Trial of the Catonsville Nine," screenplay by Daniel Berrigan and Saul Levitt; produced by Gregory Peck; directed by Gordon Davidson, ca. 1988; and poster from the Actors' Gang/Office of the Americas (OOA) staged reading of "The Trial of the Catonsville Nine," August 18, 2007.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Berrigan, Daniel.; Berrigan, Philip.; Berrigan, Jerome C.; Labrie, Ross.; McAlister, Elizabeth.
Subjects:
Antinuclear movement.; Catonsville Nine -- Trials, litigation, etc..; Catholic Church --Political participation.; Civil rights movements.; Harrisburg Seven (Trial).; Modernism (Christian theology)--Catholic Church.; Peace movements.; Plowshares Eight (Group).; Protest poetry, American.; Political activists.; Political culture.; Political plays.; Political poetry, American.; Politics in literature.; Radical theory.; Radicalism--United States.; Religion and politics--United States.; Social justice.; Student movements.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Protest movements.; Trial of the Catonsville Nine.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
The collection comprises two series. Series A is documented to item level; please refer to the card catalogue or contact a Reference librarian. Series B comprises later accessions. Within Series B, only boxes B98 and B99 are described to folder or item level.
SERIES LIST
Series I
A. Published and Unpublished Manuscripts of Daniel Berrigan
Boxes 1-58
B. Published and Unpublished Manuscripts of Philip Francis Berrigan
Boxes 59-66
C. Manuscripts of Others
Boxes 67-79
D. Documents
Boxes 80-87
E. Outgoing Correspondence of Daniel Berrigan
Boxes 88-100
F. Outgoing Correspondence of Philip Francis Berrigan
Boxes 101-106
G. Correspondence from Others
Boxes 107-147
H. Correspondence Received - Engagements
Boxes 148-152
I. Correspondence Received - Publications
Box 153
J. Correspondence Received - General
Boxes 154-189
K. Correspondence Received - General (to Philip Berrigan)
Boxes 190-196
L. Printed Materials by Daniel Berrigan
Boxes 197-217
M. Printed Materials by Philip F. Berrigan
Boxes 218-221
N. Printed Materials by Others
Boxes 222-232
O. Berriganiana
Boxes 233-257
P. Harrisburg Defense Files
Boxes 258-261
Q. Photographs
Boxes 262A, 262B
Series II
A. Daniel Berrigan Materials - 1979-1994
Boxes B1-B22, B60-B63, B76, B80, B92, B99
B. Philip Berrigan Materials - 1979-1994
Boxes B10, B23-B60, B63, B77-B79, B81-B85, B89-B90
C. Jerome C. Berrigan Materials
Boxes B48, B60, B64-B65, B87
D. Harrisburg 7 Defense Files
Boxes B67-B73
E. Correspondence Received
Boxes B98
F. Miscellaneous
Boxes B66, B74-B75, B88
G. Oversize Material
Mapcases
H. Video
DVD-120, V-209, V-815
Series III
Bound Manuscripts
Bd. Ms. 1-12
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I
  - A. Published and Unpublished Manuscripts of Daniel Berrigan (filed alphabetically by title or attributed title)
    - A-Am (Box 1)
    - An-Bl (Box 2)
    - Bo-Boq (Box 3)
    - Born-Christd (Box 4)
    - Christe-Conr (Box 5)
    - Cons-Coursd (Box 6)
    - Course Materials (Box 7-11)
    - Dar-Daz (Box 12)
    - Db-Em (Box 13)
    - Discipline of the Mountain (Box 14)
    - En-Fak (Box 15)
    - Fal-Foq (Box 16)
    - For-Fq (Box 17)
    - Fr-Hn (Box 18)
    - Ho-I L (Box 19)
    - I M-Interu (Box 20)
    - Interv-Jn (Box 21)
    - K-Let (Box 22)
    - Leu-Lig (Box 23)
    - Lights II (Box 24)
    - Lih-Love (Box 25)
    - Love-Med (Box 26)
    - Mee-Mi (Box 27)
    - Mj-Ne (Box 28)
    - Nf-Nn (Box 29)
    - No (Box 30)
    - No-[Notes] Interracial, parts 1-16 (Box 31)
    - [Notes] Interracial, parts 17-34-On (Box 32)
    - On-[Notes] Retreat (Box 33)
    - [Notes] Retreat-[Notes for sermons] (Box 34)
    - [Notes for sermons] (Box 35)
    - [Notes for talks] (Box 35-38)
    - Nov-O (Box 39)
    - P-Poe (Box 40)
    - Pof-Prison Poems [Version "A"] (Box 41)
    - Prison Poems [Version "B"]-Q (Box 42)
      Contains annotated manuscript of "The Prison Letters of Cain"
    - R-Ref (Box 43)
    - Reg-Saint R (Box 44)
    - Saint S-Sele (I) (Box 45)
    - Sele (II)-Selz (Box 46)
    - Sem-Som (Box 47)
    - Son-Std (Box 48)
    - Ten Commandments (Box 49)
    - Ste-They Call Us Dead Men [Version "A"] (Box 50)
    - They Call Us Dead Men [Version "B"]-Th (Box 51)
    - Ti-Tria (Box 52)
    - Trial (Box 53-55)
    - Trib-U (Box 56)
    - V-Wi (Box 57)
    - Wk-Z (Box 58)
  - B. Published and Unpublished Manuscripts of Philip Francis Berrigan (filed alphabetically by title or attributed title)
    - A-Leaf (Box 59)
    - Leag-[Notes for talks] (Box 60)
    - [Notes for talks] (Box 61)
    - [Notes for talks]-Prh (Box 62)
    - Pri-A Punishment for Peace, Chapter II (Box 63)
    - A Punishment for Peace, Chapter III-R (Box 64)
    - S-Wh (Box 65)
    - Wi-Z (Box 66)
  - C. Manuscripts of Others (filed alphabetically by author)
    - Berrigan, E. (Box 67)
    - Berrigan, F. (Box 68)
    - Buchman, Harold - Legal Files (Box 69-72)
    - Co-E (Box 73)
    - F (Box 74)
    - G-K (Box 75)
    - L-Mim (Box 76)
    - Min-S (Box 77)
    - T-Wa (Box 78)
    - Wb-Z (Box 79)
  - D. Documents (filed alphabetically by author)
    - A-Berrigan, Daniel (Box 80)
    - Berrigan, Daniel (Box 81-83)
      Transcripts of the trial of the Catonsville Nine appear in box 81 and 82.
    - Berrigan, Philip-L (Box 84)
    - M-R (Box 85)
    - S (Box 86)
    - T-Z (Box 87)
  - E. Outgoing Correspondence of Daniel Berrigan
    - Letters to Family, 1939-1977 (Box 88)
    - undated, 1939-1964 (Box 89)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 90)
    - 1968-May 1969 (Box 91)
    - Jun. 1969-Jan. 1971 (Box 92)
    - Feb. 1971-Aug. 1972 (Box 93)
    - Sep.-Dec. 1972 (Box 94)
    - Jan.-Oct. 1973 (Box 95)
    - Nov. 1973-Dec. 1975 (Box 96)
    - Jan. 1976-Dec. 1977 (Box 97)
    - Jan. 1978-Aug. 1978 (Box 98)
    - Sep. 1978-Dec. 1979 (Box 99)
    - Jan. 1980-Dec. 1980 (Box 100)
  - F. Outgoing Correspondence of Philip Francis Berrigan
    - 1943-1966 (Box 101)
    - 1967-Aug. 1969 (Box 102)
    - Sep. 1969-Dec. 1971 (Box 103)
    - 1972 (Box 104)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 105)
    - 1975-1984 (Box 106)
  - G. Correspondence from Others
    - A-Andersr (Box 107)
    - Anderss-Bat (Box 108)
    - Bartelme, Elizabeth (Box 109)
    - Bauer-Berrigan, Carol (Box 110)
    - Berrigan, Carol Natalie-Berrigan, Elizabeth (Box 111)
    - Berrigan, Elizabeth-Berrigan, Freda (Box 112)
    - Berrigan, Frida-Berrigan, Jerome 1943-1973 (Box 113)
    - Berrigan, Jerome 1974-1978-Berrigan, J.Z. (Box 114)
    - Berrigan, K.-Bri (Box 115)
    - Brj-Bur (Box 116)
    - Bus-Carf (Box 117)
    - Carg-Coq (Box 118)
    - Cor-Corn (Box 119)
    - Coro-Cz (Box 120)
    - D-Dd (Box 121)
    - De-Dowc (Box 122)
    - Dowd-Fink (Box 123)
    - Finl-Foq (Box 124)
    - For-Forest, James, 1972 (Box 125)
    - Forest, James, 1973-1974 (Box 126)
    - Forest, James, May 1975-Ge (Box 127)
    - Gf-Gl (Box 128)
    - Gm-Heh (Box 129)
    - Hei-Hols (Box 130)
    - Holt-Kens (Box 131)
    - Kent-Lamb, Jn (Box 132)
    - Lamb, Jo-Li (Box 133)
    - Lj-MacF (Box 134)
    - MacG-Mayer, E. (Box 135)
    - Mayer, F.-Meyer, Karl, 1962 (Box 136)
    - Meyer, Karl, 1963-Net (Box 137)
    - New-Pe (Box 138)
    - Pf-Rik (Box 139)
    - Ril-Sam (Box 140)
    - San-Sn (Box 141)
    - So-Sz (Box 142)
    - T-Tx (Box 143)
    - Ty-Walsh, S. (Box 144)
    - Walsh, T.-Waz (Box 145)
    - Wb-Wilk (Box 146)
    - Will-Z (Box 147)
  - H. Correspondence Received - Engagements
    - 1954-1965 (Box 148)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 149)
    - 1967-May 1972 (Box 150)
    - Jun. 1972-Dec. 1973 (Box 151)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 152)
  - I. Correspondence Received - Publications
    - 1950-1976 (Box 153)
  - J. Correspondence Received - General
    - 1935-1964 (Box 154)
    - 1965 (Box 155)
    - Jan.-Aug. 1966 (Box 156)
    - Sep. 1966-Jan. 1967 (Box 157)
    - Feb.-Dec. 1967 (Box 158)
    - Jan.-Mar. 1968 (Box 159)
    - Apr.-Aug. 1968 (Box 160)
    - Sep.-Dec. 1968 (Box 161)
    - 1969 (Box 162)
    - Jan.-Sep. 1970 (Box 163)
    - Oct. 1970-Dec. 1971 (Box 164)
    - Jan.-Feb. 1972 (Box 165)
    - Mar.-Jun. 1972 (Box 166)
    - Jun.-Dec. 1972 (Box 167)
    - Jan.-Jun. 1973 (Box 168)
    - Jul.-Dec. 1973 (Box 169)
    - Jan.-Sep. 1974 (Box 170)
    - Oct. 1974-Jun. 1975 (Box 171)
    - Jul. 1975-Feb. 1976 (Box 172)
    - Mar.-May 1976 (Box 173)
    - Jun.-Sep. 1976 (Box 174)
    - Oct.-Dec. 1976 (Box 175)
    - Jan.-Mar. 1977 (Box 176)
    - Mar.-May 1977 (Box 177)
    - Jun.-Aug. 1977 (Box 178)
    - Aug.-Sep. 1977 (Box 179)
    - Oct.-Dec. 1977 (Box 180)
    - Jan.-Feb. 1978 (Box 181)
    - Mar.-Apr. 1978 (Box 182)
    - May-Jul. 1978 (Box 183)
    - Aug.-Sep. 1978 (Box 184)
    - Oct.-Nov. 1978 (Box 185)
    - Dec. 1978-Feb. 1979 (Box 186)
    - Mar.-May 1979 (Box 187)
    - Jun.-Aug. 1979 (Box 188)
    - Dec. 1979-Mar. 1980 (Box 189)
  - K. Correspondence Received - General (to Philip Berrigan)
    - Sep.-Nov. 1979 (Box 190)
    - Jan.-Mar. 1980 (Box 191)
    - May 1978 [uncatalogued] (Box 192)
    - Jun. 1978 [uncatalogued] (Box 193)
    - Jul. 1978 [uncatalogued] (Box 194)
    - Aug. 1978 [uncatalogued] (Box 195)
    - Sep.-Dec. 1978 [uncatalogued] (Box 196)
  - L. Printed Materials by Daniel Berrigan (filed alphabetically by title)
    - A-Be (Box 197)
    - Bf-Com (Box 198)
    - Con-D (Box 199)
    - E-Fn (Box 200)
    - Fo-Gq (Box 201)
    - Gr-Hz (Box 202)
    - I-K (Box 203)
    - L-Letter to J (Box 204)
    - Letter to K-Lh (Box 205)
    - Li-Mn (Box 206)
    - Mo-Nn (Box 207)
    - No-On (Box 208)
    - Oo-Pn (Box 209)
    - Po-Q (Box 210)
    - R (Box 211)
    - Sa-Ss (Box 212)
    - St-Th (Box 213)
    - Ti-Trd (Box 214)
    - Tre-Trial (Box 215)
    - Trial-Tz (Box 216)
    - U-Z (Box 217)
  - M. Printed Materials by Philip F. Berrigan (filed alphabetically by title)
    - A-I (Box 218)
    - J-O (Box 219)
    - P-Ss (Box 220)
    - St-Z (Box 221)
  - N. Printed Materials by Others (filed alphabetically by title)
    - A-Be (Box 222)
    - Bf-Cor (Box 223)
    - Cos-E (Box 224)
    - F-Gq (Box 225)
    - Gr-I (Box 226)
    - J-L (Box 227)
    - M-O (Box 228)
    - P-S (Box 229)
    - T-V (Box 230)
    - W-Year (Box 231)
    - Year-Z (Box 232)
  - O. Berriganiana
    - Undated, pre-1952-1963 (Box 233)
    - 1964-1966 (Box 234)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 235)
    - 1969 (Box 236)
    - 1970 (Box 237)
    - 1971 (Box 238)
    - 1972 (Box 239)
    - 1973 (Box 240)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 241)
    - 1977 (Box 242)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 243)
    - Daniel Berrigan [file folders] (Box 244-245)
    - Philip Francis Berrigan [file folders] (Box 246-257)
  - P. Harrisburg Defense Files
    - Harrisburg Defense Files (Box 258-261)
  - Q. Photographs
    - Photographs, I. Berrigan Family (in alphabetical order) II. Other Individuals III. Mission Individuals IV. Trial of the Catonsville Nine (Box 262A, 262B)
- Series II
  - A. Daniel Berrigan Materials - 1979-1994, 1996
    - 1979 (Box B1)
    - Jan. 1980 - Aug. 1980 (Box B2)
    - Jan. 1981 - Jun. 1981 (Box B3)
    - 1981, Carbray Gift (Box B4)
    - Jul. 1981 - Mar 1982 (Box B5)
    - Sept. 1982 - Dec 1983 (Box B6)
    - 1982, 1984 (Box B7)
    - 1983 - 1985 (Box B8)
    - Apr 1982 - Apr 1984 (Box B9)
    - 1984, Marion Howe Gift (Box B10)
    - 1984 - 1985 (Box B11)
    - 1985 - 1986 (Box B12)
    - 1986 (Box B13)
    - 1986 (Box B14)
    - 1987 (Box B15)
    - Sept. 1987 - Aug. 1988 (Box B16)
    - 1988 (Box B17)
    - 1988 (Box B18)
    - 1988 - 1989 (Box B19)
    - 1988 - 1989 (Box B20)
    - 1989 - 1990 (Box B21)
    - 1990 - 1991 (Box B22)
    - 1992 (Box B60)
    - Tapes (Box B61)
    - Tapes, Records, Manuscripts (Box B62)
    - Tapes, John Deedy Gift, C-9 Film (Box B63)
    - 1991 - 1992 (Box B76)
    - 1992 - 1993 (Box B80)
    - Correspondence, Poetry, Diaries (Box B92)
    - Photograph album including photographs of festivities and attendees of Daniel Berrigan 75th Birthday Celebration, 1996 (Box B99)
  - B. Philip Berrigan Materials - 1979-1994
    - 1986 (Box B10)
    - 1979 - 1980 (Box B23-B24)
    - 1980 - 1981 (Box B25-B26)
    - 1981 (Box B27-B28)
    - 1981, Ploughshares Material (Box B29)
    - 1981 (Box B30)
    - 1981 - 1982 (Box B31)
    - 1982 (Box B32-B33)
    - 1982 - 1983 (Box B34)
    - 1983 (Box B35-B38)
    - 1984 (Box B39-B42)
    - 1984 - 1985 (Box B43-B44)
    - 1985 (Box B45-B46)
    - 1985 - 1986 (Box B47)
    - 1986 (Box B48-B50)
    - 1988 (Box B51-B52)
    - 1988 - 1989 (Box B53)
    - 1989 (Box B54)
    - 1989 - 1990 (Box B55)
    - 1990 (Box B56-B57)
    - 1991 (Box B58-B60)
    - Engraved Photographs (Box B63)
    - 1991 - 1992, Philip Berrigan, Elizabeth Mcalister (Box B77-B79)
    - 1992 - 1994, Philip Berrigan, Elizabeth Mcalister (Box B81-B85)
    - 1994 (Box B89-B90)
  - C. Jerome C. Berrigan Materials
    - 1986 (Box B48)
    - 1992 (Box B60)
    - 1980 - North Vietnam Photographs, Berriganiana (Box B64)
    - Files (Box B65)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Items and Ephemera (Box B87)
  - D. Harrisburg 7 Defense Files
    - Harrisburg 7 Defense Files (Box B67-73)
  - E. Correspondence received 1996-1997
    - John Dear, Jim Tyler, Oct. 1996, Folders marked "Answered" consist of personal, family, and pastoral letters; requests to appear, announcements, clippings, fliers; most letters first name-signed only (Box B98, Folder 1)
    - Phil Berrigan, John Dear, Oct. 1996 (Box B98, Folder 2)
    - Phil Berrigan, Ramsey Clark, Nov. 1996 (Box B98, Folder 3)
    - Jerome Berrigan, Nov. 1996 (Box B98, Folder 4)
    - Plowshares broadsides, and others, Dec. 1996 (Box B98, Folder 5)
    - John Dear, Steve Kelly; Orbis Books; broadsides, Dec. 1996 (Box B98, Folder 6)
    - John Dear, Phil Berrigan, William Sloane Coffin, Jerome Berrigan, Steve Kelly; Orbis Books, Dec. 1996 (Box B98, Folder 7)
    - Steve Kelly, William Sloane Coffin, Phil Berrigan; Trinity site exorcism, Jan. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 8)
    - Phil Berrigan, Jerome Berrigan, Steve Kelly, John Dear, Jan. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 9)
    - Phil Berrigan; Isaiah, Feb. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 10)
    - Phil Berrigan, Feb. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 11)
    - Schuyler Rhodes, John Dear, Mar. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 12)
    - Phil Berrigan, Mar. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 13)
    - Phil Berrigan, Jerome Berrigan, Liz McAllister, Mar. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 14)
    - Phil Berrigan, Jerome Berrigan, Liz McAllister, Apr. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 15)
    - Liz McAllister, Steve Kelly, Phil Berrigan, Jerome Berrigan, Apr. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 16)
    - Steve Kelly, Apr. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 17)
    - Phil Berrigan, Liz McAllister; Berrigan papers, May 1997 (Box B98, Folder 18)
    - William Stringfellow, May 1997 (Box B98, Folder 19)
    - Jerome Berrigan, Phil Berrigan, Liz McAllister, Kate (Berrigan?), Jun. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 20)
    - Phil Berrigan, Jun. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 21)
    - Jerome Berrigan, Phil Berrigan, Liz McAllister; Orbis Books, Pastoral Musicians, Jul. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 22)
    - Jul. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 23)
    - John Dear, Marian Howe, Jul. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 24)
    - Aug. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 25)
    - Phil Berrigan; Kalamazoo nephew; Berrigan papers, Aug. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 26)
    - Phil Berrigan, John Dear; Orbis Books, Aug. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 27)
    - Plowshares, Sep. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 28)
    - Liz McAllister, Phil Berrigan, Steve Kelly; Plowshares, Sep. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 29)
    - Sep. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 30)
    - Jim Forest, Jerome Berrigan, Sept. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 31)
    - John Dear; US vs. Philip Berrigan, Oct. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 32)
    - Jerome Berrigan, Oct. 1997 (Box B98, Folder 33)
  - F. Miscellaneous
    - 1970s - 1980s - Miscellaneous Backlog (Box B66)
    - Rosemary Bannan Gift (Box B74)
    - Kairos Gift (Box B75)
    - Mcvey Files (Box B88)
    - Frederic M. O'Connor, S.J. Material Correspondence, clippings, photocopies, and other material, c. 1964-70 (Box B98, Folder 34-35)
    - "Identity Crisis and Monastic Vocation" by Thomas Merton, annotated by Daniel Berrigan; other Merton material, 1964 (Box B98, Folder 36)
    - Isaiah typescript; poems, n.d. (Box B98, Folder 37)
  - G. Oversize Material
    - Oversize Material (Map-case AA-14)
    - America is Hard to Find Poster (Map-case II-7)
  - H. Video
    - Investigation of a Flame, DVD-120 (Box B61)
    - The Trial of the Catonsville Nine, V-209 (Box B61)
    - America is Hard to Find, 1970; V-815 (Box B61)
- Series III. Bound Manuscripts
  - Purgatorio, Bd. Ms. 1
    Mass market paper back, Oxford University Press edition of the work of Dante Alighieri, title page and some other pages removed, personal copy of Philip Berrigan, with pencilled annotations. Book has been removed from binding and individual sections bound with tape.
  - Demonstration photo album, Bd. Ms. 2 +
    Album of photographs of Philip Berrigan and other people at several sites; no dates given; photographer/s unknown; various signs and banners displayed; some photos depict interactions with police. There is also a work of graphic art by George Knowlton.
  - Prison and the Christian Resister: The Letters and Journals from Prison of Daniel and Philip Berrigan, Bd. Ms. 3 +
    M.A. Thesis SUNY Buffalo, pertains to the lives and activities, prior to 1976, of Daniel and Philip Berrigan, Catholic priests active in peace and social justice causes by Sara J. McLaughlin.
  - Religion and radicalism: the American "Catholic Left" as a social movement, Bd. Ms. 4 +
    PhD dissertation prepared at Columbia University by Charles A. Meconis. Found (with papers from Daniel Berrigan of early 1981) in a box labelled (by Meconis?) "to Prof. Gilllian Lindt from: Charles A. Meconis PhD. (Cand.) re: Defense copy of dissertation." With the dissertation were found typed and handwritten comments by Elizabeth (McAlister) Berrigan, Philip Francis Berrigan, and Daniel Berrigan; these have been removed and separately cataloged under Berrigan, Elizabeth (McAlister). The title page was lacking, and Philip Berrigan's comments were written on the copyright page; therefore, the dissertation has been bound with replacement title page and copyright page. Cf. the book (N.Y.: Seabury 1979) by Charles A. Meconis, With clumsy grace: the American Catholic left, 1961-1975.
  - [Unused numbers], Bd. Ms. 5 & 6
  - The Petrean, Bd. Ms. 7 + v.1-3
    Yearbook of St. Peter's Preparatory School, Jersey City, New Jersey, 1947-1949.
  - Blue Book, 1957, Bd. Ms. 8 +
    Yearbook of Brooklyn Preparatory School, Brooklyn, N.Y.
  - Pity the nation.., Bd. Ms. 9 +
    This is a bound script of a drama about a 1969 trial in Milwaukee, Wisconsin. The author has signed the manuscript with a note to Daniel Berrigan, by James Sage.
  - Daniel Berrigan, S.J.: A bibliography of criticism, with an introductory essay on his critical reputation, Bd. Ms. 10 +
    MA thesis prepared at the University of Maryland by Carol Ann Rittner. Thesis is concerned with interpretation and critical reception of Daniel Berrigan's published works.
  - Daniel Berrigan scrapbook, Bd. Ms. 11 ++
    Scrapbook contains newspaper clippings, photos, programs, and writings assembled by Daniel Berrigan in his youth. There is material about various Berrigan family members: John Berrigan, Jerome Berrigan, Edmund Berrigan, Agnes Berrigan, etc. There are early writings by Daniel Berrigan and a poem by John Berrigan. Selection of clippings prefigures some of Daniel Berrigan's adult interests in civil rights and resistance to civil authority when in conflict with religious idealism.
  - Daniel Berrigan poetry, Bd. Ms. 12 +
    Consists of a collection of Daniel Berrigan's poetic works, copied and bound together.
OTHER GUIDES TO THE COLLECTION
A card catalogue is available providing item-level description of Series A of the collection.